{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Many people fled this event on boats whose high passenger mortality rates inspired the nickname “coffin ships.” During this event, the phrase “taking the soup” was used to refer to families who accepted charity in exchange for converting to the Protestant faith. Robert Peel repealed the Corn Laws to provide relief forthose impactedby, forten points, what1840s disastercausedby aphytophthora [FI-toe-THO-rah] blight of a certain crop?",
      "answer": [
        "Irish Potato Famine",
        "the Great Famine",
        "the Great Hunger"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer quoted “Come, my dearest, why so sad this morning,” in a piece written to benefit wounded Serbian soldiers in 1876. This composer celebrated Romanov imperialism with the polonaise that ends his Symphony no. 3, “Polish.” This composer of the Marche Slave used “La Marseillaise” to represent Napoleon’s invading army in an overture that, when played in the US, often accompanies fireworks. For ten points, name this Russian composer who included cannons in his 1812 Overture.",
      "answer": "Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "At age 21, this man founded a group modeled on English coffeehouses called the Junto. After partnering with Hugh Meredith, this man founded a short-lived publication that was the first German language paper in America. In an essay titled The Way of Wealth, this man claimed that “There are no gains without pains,” one of many maxims collected in an annual series that ran from 1732 to 1758 under the name Poor Richard’s Almanac. For ten points, name this Founding Father on the $100 bill.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body of water is home to the Isla del Sol and the Isla de la Luna, each of which contain ruins of a 15th-century civilization that flourished around its shores. Amantani Island is located on this lake and is currently home to thousands of Quechua-speaking peoples. This lake was viewed as sacred by the Incans, and is described as the highest navigable lake in the world. For ten points, name this lake that straddles the Bolivia-Peru border and is the largest lake in South America.",
      "answer": "Lake Titicaca"
    },
    {
      "question": "This province’s Quiet Revolution secularized society in the 1960s. The Meech Lake and Charlottetown Accords tried to better integrate this province with its country. A 1995 referendum narrowly rejected independence for this province, where a 1970 crisis required the first peacetime use of the War Measures Act after the FLQ kidnapped Pierre Laporte in Montreal. For ten points, name this French-speaking Canadian province.",
      "answer": "Quebec"
    },
    {
      "question": "Robert La Follette believed that his Senate office was burgled because he led an investigation into this event. The Supreme Court ruled Congress could compel testimony in a case about this event, which AttorneyGeneralHarryDaughertywasaccusedofnotinvestigating.ThisscandalrevolvedaroundEdward Doheny and Harry Sinclair’s bribing of Secretary of the Interior Albert Fall for contracts to oil fields in Wyoming. For ten points, name this scandal that plagued Warren Harding’s administration in 1922.",
      "answer": "Teapot Dome scandal"
    },
    {
      "question": "At the end of his life, Marcus Aurelius told those around him “weep not for me; think rather” of those affected by one of these disasters; that disaster began during the reign of Antoninus Pius and is sometimes named after Galen. The port of Piraeus [pi-ray-us] is the estimated starting point of one of these disasters that began in 430 BC in Athens. Under Justinian, over 20 million people were killed in one of these that was caused by Yersinia pestis. Bubonic is a type of, for ten points, what type of widely-spreading disease?",
      "answer": [
        "plagues",
        "Antonine Plague",
        "Plague of Galen",
        "Plague of Athens",
        "Plague of Justinian",
        "bubonic plague"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event may have been called out of anger over Urban VIII’s presentation as Simplicio in Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems. After this event, the central figure allegedly said “and yet it moves,” a refusal to accept this event’s result. This event began with the accusation of teaching a “false doctrine” “that the Sun is the center of the world.” The Roman Inquisition carried out, for ten points, what 17th century affair over an Italian astronomer’s heliocentrism?",
      "answer": [
        "the trial of Galileo Galilei",
        "additional information"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city’s Kew Garden area, 38 neighbors allegedly watched Winston Moseley murder Kitty Genovese. In 1989, Matias Reyes committed a crime in this city but only confessed in 2002, well after full-page ads demanding the death penalty were made by Donald Trump. The Son of Sam murdered people during the summer of 1976 in, for ten points, what city whose police wrongly caught the Central Park Five?",
      "answer": "New York City or NYC"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two answers required. These two people criticized critical reformers of Christianity, particularly Bruno Bauer, in a book titled The Holy Family. The League of the Just asked these two people to collaborate on an 1848 pamphlet that opens by stating “a specter is haunting Europe” and studies the history of class struggles. For ten points, name these German philosophers, the co-authors of The Communist Manifesto.",
      "answer": [
        "Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels",
        "in either order"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Early members of this organization included Gustave Moynier, who caused a rift in its early years. The first Nobel Peace Prize was awarded jointly to pacifist Fr´ed´eric Passy and the founder of this organization, Henri Dunant, who was inspired after witnessing the carnage of the Battle of Solferino. For ten points, name this Geneva-based international organization that protects victims of war and whose member societies often provide medical services in disaster areas.",
        "answer": [
          "International Committee of the Red Cross",
          "International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to Dunant’s Nobel Peace Prize and the three Nobel Prizes given to the International Committee of the Red Cross, this President of the American Red Cross won the prize in 1953. This American statesman names a foreign aid plan that rebuilt Western Europe after World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "George Marshall",
          "Marshall Plan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This team was on the losing end of Don Larsen’s World Series perfect game in 1956. In that year and seven others, this team lost to the Yankees in the World Series, though they won the 1955 World Series behind Duke Snider, Roy Campanella, rookie Sandy Koufax, and an infielder signed by Branch Rickey in 1947. For ten points, name this Major League Baseball team that moved to southern California in 1957 and broke the color barrier by signing Jackie Robinson to play in Brooklyn.",
        "answer": [
          "Brooklyn Dodgers",
          "Los Angeles Dodgers after “seven others” is read",
          "Brooklyn until it is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Larsen’s perfect game was described as “the biggest diamond in the biggest ring” by this broadcaster, who called that game and thousands of others during his 67-year career with the Dodgers. He retired in 2016.",
        "answer": "Vincent “Vin” Scully"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these entities was killed by Tissarakkha in anger at the reverence given to it by Ashoka; a descendant of that entity can be found today at Bodh Gaya. In the 19th century, Karl Budde argued about the number of these entities in the Garden of Eden. One of these entities connected the nine worlds in Norse mythology and was known as Yggdrasil. The Buddha reached enlightenment under, for ten points, what kind of plant that, in the Garden of Eden, represents the knowledge of good and evil?",
        "answer": "trees"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Siddhartha Gautama reached enlightenment sitting under this fig tree.",
        "answer": "the Bodhi tree"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This group was compromised during an incident in Media, Pennsylvania when the “Citizen’s Commission” raided one of its member’s homes, recovering files that detailed this group’s COINTELPRO program. An infamous letter encouraging Martin Luther King to commit suicide was written and sent by this agency under the direction of Clyde Tolson’s mentor. For ten points, name this domestic American security service led by J. Edgar Hoover.",
        "answer": "Federal Bureau of Investigation or FBI"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "COINTELPRO got the authorization to tap Martin Luther King’s phone from this Attorney General. In 1968, this man gave an impromptu speech after King’s assassination that probably stopped riots from breaking out in Indianapolis.",
        "answer": [
          "Robert Francis “Bobby” Kennedy or RFK",
          "Bobby Kennedy"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this region, the Battle of Gergovia allowed some natives to keep their independence. In a 52 BC battle in this region, the attacking side built a wall around a besieged town, then built another wall around themselves. A work written about this region notes that it is “a whole divided into three parts” and describes the author’s victory over Vercingetorix at Alesia. For ten points, name this region that was conquered by Julius Caesar and largely corresponds with modern-day France.",
        "answer": "Gaul or Gallia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As mentioned, Caesar divided Gaul into three provinces: Celtica, Belgica, and this region in modern southwest France. A millennium later, this region became English after Henry II married Eleanor. You can give either its Latin or modern name.",
        "answer": [
          "Aquitaine",
          "Gallia Aquitania"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was led by Veselin Duranovic [dur-AH-no-VITCH] after the death of its longtime leader in 1980. A partisan resistance to the Nazi occupation of this country established a Communist government after the war, led by Josip Tito. The 1992 breakup of this country led to war crimes such as the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-neet-zah] Massacre and the Siege of Sarajevo. For ten points, name this federal Balkan country that included Serbia and Croatia.",
        "answer": "Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Serbian leader oversaw the breakup of Yugoslavia and was charged with war crimes in Kosovo, but died of a heart attack in 2006 during his trial in the Hague.",
        "answer": "Slobodan Milosevic , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this century, the political slogan “sonno joi” responded to the arrival of the “black ships.” The Convention of Kanagawa was signed during this century, ending a longstanding policy of isolation. The Tokugawa Shogunate was overthrown in this century as part of a restoration of imperial power in Japan. For ten points, name this century in which the Japanese navy purchased the CSS Stonewall four years after the end of the American Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "19th century",
          "1800s"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned 1868 restoration of imperial power was led by, and named for, this Japanese emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Emperor Meiji",
          "Mutsuhito",
          "Meiji Restoration",
          "similar terms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Indian Bureau was reformed under this President after Secretary of the Interior Columbus Delano was dismissed for bribery. This man’s administration was rattled by revelations that Oakes Ames’s company siphoned funds from the Union Pacific railroad and bribed politicians. This man’s private secretary, Orville Babcock, helped St. Louis distillers create an infamous Whiskey Ring. A widely corrupt administration plagued, for ten points, what 18th US President and former Civil War general?",
        "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Oakes Ames was in charge of this railroad construction company, a shell corporation formed by Union Pacific to assist in fleecing the US government. This company names the ensuing scandal.",
        "answer": [
          "Credit Mobilier of America",
          "Credit Mobilier"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Civil War Battles",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Battle where a cemetery dedication included Abraham Lincoln’s famous address.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Gettysburg",
            "Gettysburg Address, cemetery, battlefield, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First major battle of the Civil War, where Irvin McDowell’s poorly trained Union army was defeated by P.G.T. Beauregard.",
          "answer": [
            "First Battle of Bull Run or Battle of First Manassas",
            "propmt on partial answers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Georgia city burned at the start of Sherman’s March to the Sea.",
          "answer": "Atlanta"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where the Union Admiral Farragut shouted “damn the torpedoes, full steam ahead!” and captured the port of Mobile.",
          "answer": "Alabama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Waterway that split the Confederacy after the capture of Vicksburg.",
          "answer": "Mississippi River"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where Albert Sidney Johnston died in fighting at Shiloh.",
          "answer": "Tennessee"
        },
        {
          "question": "1864 Confederate victory where Grant launched a futile frontal assault near Richmond.",
          "answer": "Battle of Cold Harbor"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 battle where Simon Bolivar Buckner surrendered to Grant, the first Confederate general to do so.",
          "answer": "Battle of Fort Donelson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The KGB",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nation whose main intelligence agency was the KGB from 1954 to 1991.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "USSR",
            "CCCP",
            "SSSR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Current world leader who once served as a KGB agent.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Putin"
        },
        {
          "question": "American counterpart of the KGB whose leaders have included Allen Dulles.",
          "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency or CIA"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where the KGB could not control Kabul or defeat the mujahideen during a 1980s war.",
          "answer": "Islamic Republic of Afghanistan"
        },
        {
          "question": "European country where Imre Nagy’s [im-reh nazh’s] 1956 revolt was violently crushed by the KGB.",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "KGB chairman from 1967 to 1982 who briefly succeeded Leonid Brezhnev as a world leader.",
          "answer": "Yuri Andropov"
        },
        {
          "question": "British spy ring, including Kim Philby, who passed confidential information to the KGB during the 1940s and 50s.",
          "answer": [
            "Cambridge Five",
            "Cambridge Four",
            "Cambridge Spy Ring, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Building formerly used as KGB headquarters and which once notoriously housed political prisoners on the ground floor.",
          "answer": "Lubyanka Gandhi Political Power If an answer in this round is a person with the last name Gandhi, give their full first name. You will not"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "be prompted for responding “Gandhi.” Name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the be prompted for responding “gandhi.” name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nonviolent Indian independence leader known as Bapu, who was shot by Nathuram Godse in 1948.",
          "answer": [
            "Mohandas Gandhi",
            "Mahatma Gandhi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British monopoly he protested by marching to the sea at Dandi.",
          "answer": "salt march"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unrelated woman who was the first Prime Minister of India.",
          "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of now-banned test she oversaw in 1974, codenamed “Smiling Buddha.”",
          "answer": [
            "nuclear weapons test",
            "anything related to testing a nuclear/atomic bomb"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1984 military operation she authorized in Amritsar, a siege of the Golden Temple.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Blue Star",
            "Operation Metal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious background of the group attacked in that operation, as well as of her bodyguards, who assassinated her after that operation.",
          "answer": "Sikhism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Her son, who succeeded her as Prime Minister and was assassinated himself in 1991.",
          "answer": "Rajiv Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lower house of Indian Parliament in which he served before becoming Prime Minister.",
          "answer": "Lok Sabha"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man employed logs to hamper paratroop landings, a tactic that became known as his namesake Asparagus when this man oversaw defenses at the Atlantic (20 pts)",
        "Wall. While this man recovered from injuries sustained in a strafing raid, he was offered cyanide pills after he was implicated in the Valkyrie assassination plot against (10 pts)",
        "Hitler. This general fought an indecisive battle against Bernard Montgomery at El Alamein. For ten points, name this “Desert Fox” who commanded Germany’s Afrika Korps."
      ],
      "answer": "Erwin Rommel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A character created by this author has thousands of children with his concubines who are born after seven month pregnancies. This author wrote about The General in The Autumn of the Patriarch and described the final days of (20 pts)",
        "Simon Bolivar in The General in His Labyrinth. This author fictionalized a 1928 massacre of striking banana workers in Ci´enaga, a town in his native (10 pts)",
        "Colombia. For ten points, name this Nobel Prize-winning author of One Hundred Years of Solitude."
      ],
      "answer": "Gabriel Garcia Marquez"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The outcome of this Supreme Court case helped trigger an economic panic that included the failure of the Ohio Life Insurance and Trust Company. John McLean and Benjamin Curtis (20 pts)",
        "dissented from the majority opinion in this case, citing a lack of opposition to similar provisions in the Northwest Ordinance. The plaintiff of this case sued Irene (10 pts)",
        "Emerson, but was found not to have standing to sue for his freedom. For ten points, name this 1857 case in which Roger Taney [taw-nee] declared that African-Americans were not citizens."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dred Scott v. Sandford",
        "either underlined portion",
        "Dred Scott v Sanford"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Joseph Ni´epce [nee-EPS] was one of the first practitioners of this medium, using it to create a view from his house. The 291 studio focused on this medium under the management of (20 pts)",
        "Alfred Stieglitz. This medium was advanced by Louis Daguerre, who names an early form of this medium that reduced the necessary (10 pts)",
        "exposure time. For ten points, name this artistic process that Ansel Adams used to portray scenes from American national parks in the 20th century."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "photography",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This industry’s poor sanitation control led to a contamination of the South Fork, where decomposing products led it to be called “Bubbly Creek.” In another incident, this industry’s so-called “embalmed” product killed Nelson (20 pts)",
        "Miles’ men during the Spanish-American War. Morris, Swift, and Armour were once the biggest companies in this industry, which was targeted by the (10 pts)",
        "Pure Food and Drug Act in 1906. For ten points, name this industry that was centered in Chicago at the time of Upton Sinclair’s The Jungle. ANSWER:meatpackingindustry(acceptwordforms;acceptdescriptiveanswersinvolvingslaughtering, processing,and/orshippingmeat;promptonpartialanswers,suchas“agriculture,”“meat,”“shipping,” etc.; prompt on butchering and word forms) (6) This state’s Lake Moultrie was created during the Great Depression and named for one of its governors after the Revolutionary War. In 1781, Daniel Morgan’s defeat of (+) Banastre Tarleton forced the British out of this state. The northernmost Sea Islands are located in this state, which contains The (*) Citadel, a military college. For ten points, name this state, the site of the Revolutionary War’s Waxhaws Massacre and Battle of Cowpens, each of which were fought well north of Columbia, its capital."
      ],
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On a voyage to Panama, this man made a detour to attack the Canary Islands at the Battle of Las Palmas. During his Great Expedition, this privateer raided St. Augustine. With his cousin John Hawkins, this man organized (20 pts)",
        "fireships and won against a fleet led by the Duke of Medina Sidonia. In 1587, this captain raided Cadiz, “singing the beard of the King of Spain,” seven years after a landmark voyage on the (10 pts)",
        "Golden Hind. For ten points, name this man, the first Englishman to circumnavigate the globe, who was employed by Elizabeth I and fought the Spanish Armada."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This king is often speculated to be Amraphel, the Biblical king of Shinar. Shortly before his death, this king defeated Ishme-Dagan I and forced Assyria to pay tribute to him. This king’s most famous creation was a set of 282 (20 pts)",
        "rules discovered in Susa in 1901. This ruler is depicted with Shamash at the top of an Akkadian-language monument that commands, “If a man destroy the (10 pts)",
        "eye of another man, they shall destroy his eye.” For ten points, name this Babylonian ruler who wrote an early law code."
      ],
      "answer": "Hammurabi"
    }
  ]
}